<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-04-23T21:04:48+12:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/</id><title type="html">Michael Dowse</title><subtitle>Software Developer, reader, and occasional blogger. Founder of Go Vocab. Born and raised in Wellington, New Zealand.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Decoupling isn’t just for developers</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2017/04/23/decoupling.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoupling isn't just for developers" /><published>2017-04-23T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2017-04-23T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2017/04/23/decoupling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2017/04/23/decoupling.html">&lt;p&gt;A while ago I read this article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/complexity-and-strategy-325cd7f59a92&quot;&gt;Complexity and Strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend reading it. It’s much better than any of my blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sentence that still lingers in my mind two months later is this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Features interact — intentionally — and that makes the cost of implementing the N+1 feature closer to N than 1.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In every organisation I’ve been a part of it goes this way: At first adding new features is fast and easy but as the codebase grows, it gets exponentially harder and slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always ascribed this to technical debt, but that never felt quite right. The codebases weren’t that bad, yet adding new features still kept getting harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it all makes sense. New features usually interact with existing features, so the more existing features there are that need to be interacted with, the harder it is to add a new feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a good example of this in Slack just now. I write most of my blog posts, including this one, while on vacation. When I left work I used Slack’s new “status” feature to set my status to one of the defaults: “Vacationing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was suprised to find that setting my status in this way did not affect my notification settings in any way. I kept getting notifications from my workmates until I used a separate feature to “Snooze Notifications”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The status feature is completely decoupled from the notification settings functionality. They do not interact in any way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was initially suprised that setting my status to “Vacationing” did not change my notification settings, can you imagine the confusion if it had? Even if it was well communicated in the UI, it would leave me confused about how different statuses affected my notifications. What if I set my status to “At Lunch”, would I expect that to also mute notifications? What if I ignored the default statuses and created a custom status of “On Holiday”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decoupled features are generally easier for users to understand than features that interact with one another in complex ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why Slack did this, it helps to understand the context: The notifications functionality is already very complex. Check out this diagram of how Slack decides whether to send a notification:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;When Hacker News commenters say &amp;quot;I could build that app in a weekend!&amp;quot; I think of this chart of how Slack decides to send a notification. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LopicAyzkL&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/LopicAyzkL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Matt Haughey (@mathowie) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mathowie/status/837735473745289218&quot;&gt;March 3, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack already have a lot of features that interact with notification settings in a complex way, if they had designed statuses to interact with notification settings as well it would have vastly increased the cost of adding this new feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding features in a decoupled way like Slack did with Statuses avoids interactions between features which reduces overall complexity in the system and makes it easier to add new functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good developers are always trying to decouple things, to minify the ways in which different pieces of code interact with each other. It’s one of the main selling points of the current hot trend: microservices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decoupling can’t be purely the concern of developers though. Software architecture and product design are inescapably linked. If the product design specifies that features interact with each other, then to a certain extent the developers’ hands are tied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean product designers need to understand software architecture, microservices and decoupling. Nor does it mean that we should elevate technical concerns over user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we need to be conscious of the ways features interact with one another. To understand that interactions between features add complexity to the product and that complexity is expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex interactions between features can make it harder for users to understand how the product works, and are guaranteed to slow down development of new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, let us go forth and make trade-offs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A while ago I read this article: Complexity and Strategy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Design cycles</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2017/02/27/design-cycles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design cycles" /><published>2017-02-27T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2017-02-27T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2017/02/27/design-cycles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2017/02/27/design-cycles.html">&lt;p&gt;You are a startup. You know design is important. It’s so important that you hire a super talented designer to make sure everything you make is beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your designer produces a beautiful new design for your homepage which they predict will boost conversions. You need conversions. You are losing money. You get a developer onto it straight away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two years pass by…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have interfaces everywhere, not because distributed systems are on trend right now but because your customers are distributed. There’s the public website, the web app, the mobile version of the website, the iphone app, the android app, the Tumblr blog, the API documentation, the SaaS Job Board product you’ve integrated with and written a custom theme for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are emails as well of course; some from your app and some from your marketing automation system, plus the life cycle emails from that other SaaS product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re launching a new page of your website targeting a new niche of customers. Your designer has done some designs in a super cool new style. It will probably increase conversions, you get a developer onto it straight away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, the new designs for the new page don’t really match the rest of the site. It’s kind of a different style. The skeumorphic buttons are out, flat rectangles are in. Textured backgrounds are out, huge background images are in. The logo and branding is the same though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think of it, nothing really matches. The mobile site looks a bit outdated, but you have apps now. The apps look a bit different to the web app, but your iOS developer is busy on another project. The public facing site looks great, it gets updated the most so it has the latest designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inconsistency bothers you, it’s a bad experience for your customers and it doesn’t look good to prospects, it might even be affecting conversion rates. Design is important. Not more important that conversions or course, but still, it would be nice if everything matched the nice new designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are not alone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit your banks website, it probably looks pretty nice, that’s because it’s trying to convert you. Now log into online banking, probably not so nice. Now try logging in to your banks online business banking portal, the ones I have seen are all about a decade behind the design of the banks home page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to pick on banks, but every startup that’s been around for more than a couple of years struggles to maintain a cohesive look and feel across all customer touchpoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple reasons for this, one I’ve been thinking about lately is about cycle times. More specifically, about the mismatch between an organisation’s design cycle time and its design implementation cycle time. Those are terms I made up, but you can think of them something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design Cycle Time:&lt;/strong&gt; How frequently our visual style changes or evolves, this varies depending on the designer/design team, brand changes as you seek product/market fit etc. For example, it could be about 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design Implementation Cycle Time:&lt;/strong&gt; The time it takes for all your interfaces to be updated to a new design. In my experience this varies from 3 months to infinite (all interfaces are never brought into alignment), with the median around 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your Design Cycle Time is 6 months, and your Design Implementation Cycle Time is 2 years. The customer experience won’t be terrible, but it won’t cohesive, and that holds it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;To ensure a mostly consistent customer experience most of the time, a companies design implementation cycle time must be significantly shorter than its design cycle time.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In framing the problem this way, two approaches to solving it emerge: increasing design cycle time, or reducing design implementation cycle time. Ideally both approaches would be pursued in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before tackling cycle times though, it is essential to understand your interfaces. I’ve never witnessed a ‘complete redesign’ that managed to update every customer touchpoint. There’s always something that gets missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the merch store? What about the knowledge base? What about the monthly newsletter? These are the less important customer touchpoints but they all contribute to that feeling of cohesion, where the experience just feels right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all of your interfaces are documented, then you can begin to make improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-increase-design-cycle-time&quot;&gt;To increase Design Cycle Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid trends, stick to the classics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design in a wider context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep short lived designs contained:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes visual styles have to change fast, that’s how marketing campaigns work. They just need to be treated as such. Design changes for a particular campaign should be implemented as a skin, or theme across the more permanent “evergreen” style to make removing them at the end of the campaign simple.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-decrease-design-implementation-cycle-time&quot;&gt;To decrease Design Implementation Cycle Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know your interfaces:&lt;/strong&gt; Know what interfaces you have, where they are and maintain the capability to update them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pattern Libraries:&lt;/strong&gt; A topic for another blog post, but a well maintained and used pattern library really is the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update designs by default:&lt;/strong&gt; When working on an interface, never leave a interface without updating the design.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You are a startup. You know design is important. It’s so important that you hire a super talented designer to make sure everything you make is beautiful.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Money</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/08/19/money.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money" /><published>2016-08-19T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/08/19/money</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/08/19/money.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In a capitalist society a dollar is a vote.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have the luxury of choosing then the way we choose to spend out money is an expression of our values is an expression of our values. Intentionally or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My favourite shops by number of visits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;column-sixth&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tommy Millions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-sixth&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gentlemens Beans [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-sixth&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TJ Katsu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-sixth&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Peoples Coffee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-sixth&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Little Penang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-sixth&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sixes &amp;amp; Sevens&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;clear&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to spend in a responsible way, considering the direct &amp;amp; indirect consequences of my purchases. Not all my spending is conscious in this way, it’s hard work to put so much thought into each purchase. Some heuristics are now starting to emerge which I hope to document soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some (unordered) attributes I think about when spending money consciously:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consumption of the product is good for me personally&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My consumption of the product is not detrimental to society as a whole&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The company treats staff well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sustainable supply chain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The end product is sustainable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s how I’ve been going for the last 12 months [2]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;column-third&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reflects values&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;e.g. Air New Zealand, Peoples Coffee, Little Penang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-third&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Doesn't reflect values&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;e.g. TJ Katsu, The Warehouse, BP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;column-third&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;dots&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not sure&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;e.g. Bunnings, Countdown, New World&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;clear&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping that as I make decisions on certain products (e.g. where to buy coffee) that don’t need to be repeated the percentage of conscious spending will increase. That’s the theory at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;[1] Highly underestimated as I often have a prepaid coffee card&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;[2] This is just my personal spending which is far outweighed by household spending&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In a capitalist society a dollar is a vote.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tasty</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/04/17/tasty.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tasty" /><published>2016-04-17T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2016-04-17T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/04/17/tasty</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/04/17/tasty.html">&lt;p&gt;If you use Facebook, you’ve probably noticed the recipe videos from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/buzzfeedtasty/?fref=ts&quot;&gt;Tasty&lt;/a&gt; frequently featuring on your news feed. They’re everywhere right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go viral on Facebook a video needs to catch your attention, without any sound, while you’re scrolling through the news feed. The Tasty videos do that, I stop scrolling every time. Here’s one for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fbuzzfeedtasty%2Fvideos%2F1741611326091509%2F&amp;amp;show_text=1&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;425&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, I wasn’t particularly surprised to find out that Tasty is a part of Buzzfeed. I normally don’t like viral things in my feed but I do like these Tasty videos and I’ve been able to rationalise a couple of possible justifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooking is a good thing that we should do more of and Tasty videos encourage that&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people agree that we should cook more. Just like we should exercise more, or read more books. These are things that most people feel are positive influences on their lives, and that we should do more of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could say that reality shows like MasterChef encourage cooking, and for some people they probably do, but they also promote sitting on the couch watching other people cook, and then paying exorbitant prices to eat a meal prepared in a kitched overseen by a “MasterChef”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasty videos serve less as entertainment and more as inspiration. While you couldn’t make the meal just from watching the video, you &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; could, and there’s always a link to the full recipe attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They promote &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; cooking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasty recipes tend to start from scratch, using basic ingredients. There are no cake mixes, or pre-made anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only inputs into the videos are relatively unprocessed ingredients that can be found in any supermarket, showing a committment to recipes that people can actually make at home. It’s just good business sense really, as the recipes need to appeal to people all over the world. Some of the competitors who have popped up are less principled, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/foodbyshared/videos/1018342061536144/?fref=nf&quot;&gt;like this example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipes are often not particularly simple (though the video format makes them look deceptively so). They encourage the idea that cooking takes effort, but that your effort will be rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convinced? Here’s a couple more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fbuzzfeedtasty%2Fvideos%2F1741600096092632%2F&amp;amp;show_text=1&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;425&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fbuzzfeedtasty%2Fvideos%2F1741588772760431%2F&amp;amp;show_text=1&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;425&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you use Facebook, you’ve probably noticed the recipe videos from Tasty frequently featuring on your news feed. They’re everywhere right now.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing a Socially Responsible Kiwisaver Scheme</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/03/10/kiwisaver.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing a Socially Responsible Kiwisaver Scheme" /><published>2016-03-10T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2016-03-10T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/03/10/kiwisaver</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/03/10/kiwisaver.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently found myself making significant contributions to Kiwisaver for the first time so I decided to put an appropriate amount of effort into choosing the best Kiwisaver scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all my spending, I try to follow Ghandi’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/30/opinion/falser-words-were-never-spoken.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;misquoted&lt;/a&gt; advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  Be the change that you wish to see in the world
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to investing, this means investing in companies which are making a positive contribution to society &amp;amp; the environment. From my cursory analysis of the 189 available Kiwisaver schemes there are 5 that are specifically targeted at investors like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quaystreet-balanced-sri-fund&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/craigs-investment-partners-kiwistart-defined-scheme---balanced-sri-fund-craigs-investment-partners-/&quot;&gt;QuayStreet Balanced SRI Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Craigs Investment Partners&lt;/em&gt; this fund invests in investments that Craigs “deems to be environmentally sustainable or socially responsible”. A pretty broad mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Balanced&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 318&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $4,713,552&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socially-responsible-investment-growth-fund&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/grosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited/&quot;&gt;Socially Responsible Investment Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Grosvenor Investment Management&lt;/em&gt;, this fund “will exclude companies and other investments where the underlying activities are principally involved in the tobacco, alcohol, gambling and armaments industries” which is a pretty low bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Growth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 1,556&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $16,999,866&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socially-responsible-investment-balanced-fund&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/grosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-balanced-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited/&quot;&gt;Socially Responsible Investment Balanced Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Grosvenor Investment Management&lt;/em&gt;, this fund will exclude “investments which do not satisfy certain socially responsible investment criteria”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Balanced&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 4,031&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $17,854,622&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sustainable-international-share-fund&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/oneanswer-kiwisaver-scheme---sustainable-international-share-fund-anz-new-zealand-investments-limited/&quot;&gt;Sustainable International Share Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;ANZ&lt;/em&gt;, this fund invests exclusively in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://funds.ft.com/uk/Tearsheet/Summary?s=LU0119216553:EUR&quot;&gt;Global Sustainable Equity Fund&lt;/a&gt; which “combines respect for social principles (such as human rights, non-discrimination and the issue of child labour) and environmental principles with good financial prospects”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite only investing on one fund, this scheme still manages to charge above average fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Aggressive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 362&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $4,305,412&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ethica-fund&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/superlife---ethica-pool-superlife-limited/&quot;&gt;Ethica Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Superlife&lt;/em&gt;, this fund “looks to avoid investments in the areas of pornography, gambling, tobacco, alcohol, armaments and fossil fuel extraction”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Balanced&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 937&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $12,406,942&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other options. Craigs offers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigsip.com/services/kiwisaver.aspx&quot;&gt;a scheme where you can pick your own stocks&lt;/a&gt;, and there may be other schemes which invest in a responsible manner but don’t explicitly flag that as their intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking purely at social responsibility it seems like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/grosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited/&quot;&gt;Socially Responsible Investment Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt; is the best option, but I will be following up some of the others for more details of their investment criteria. There are other factors to consider of course, such as risk profile, returns, and fees.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently found myself making significant contributions to Kiwisaver for the first time so I decided to put an appropriate amount of effort into choosing the best Kiwisaver scheme.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Plymouth</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/new-plymouth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Plymouth" /><published>2015-12-19T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2015-12-19T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/new-plymouth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/new-plymouth.html">&lt;p&gt;New Plymouth is a lot cooler than it used to be. Som and I headed up there for the weekend a few months ago. In no particular order, some highlights were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-coastal-walkway&quot;&gt;The coastal walkway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/walkway.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coastal walkway is lovely, the water was a bit wild the day we went which made it all the more interesting. Unfortunately not caught on camera: when Som turned to photograph this sign a wave came up from behind and she got soaked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-govett-brewster-len-lye-gallery&quot;&gt;The Govett-Brewster Len Lye gallery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/lenlye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exterior is probably actually the highlight, but the stuff inside is cool too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mount-taranaki&quot;&gt;Mount Taranaki&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/taranaki.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was too much snow to climb Mount Taranaki without actual mountaineering skills but I’ve climbed it on a previous trip and it’s a pretty awesome hike. When we went in the height of summer there was still snow at the top. If nothing else, it’s worth a trip to the visitors center halfway up the mountain for some sweet views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;street-art&quot;&gt;Street Art&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/bmd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Plymouth is the home of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmdisyourfriend.com/&quot;&gt;BMD&lt;/a&gt; and there is a lot of their work, and cool work by other artists, throughout the city center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;food--drink-that-was-up-to-the-standard-of-us-city-folk&quot;&gt;Food &amp;amp; drink that was up to the standard of us city folk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For coffee, head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ozonecoffee.com/bean-store.php&quot;&gt;Ozone Coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For brunch, head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thefederalstore.com/&quot;&gt;The Federal Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For dinner, head to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/PEKAREN-696952050381686/&quot;&gt;Pekaren&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus:&lt;/strong&gt; Our AirBnB host was a nudist with a house full of &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; artwork, though the wall to wall mirrors in the shower were a little intimidating.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">New Plymouth is a lot cooler than it used to be. Som and I headed up there for the weekend a few months ago. In no particular order, some highlights were:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rules of the blog</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/blogging-goals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rules of the blog" /><published>2015-12-19T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2015-12-19T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/blogging-goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/blogging-goals.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve always struggled with blogging. I want to do it, I have things that I want to share. But it always happens in bursts, a few good posts create a high bar for future posts, which get half written but never published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly I agonise over what I should be blogging about. Should I post my travel pictures? Should I be posting my own introspections? Or should I be posting my commentary on things? To help reduce my future agonising I’ve come up with two rules for this blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Posts things of interest to others&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a public blog, not a personal diary. It’s not for my aimless musings. I mean it is for that, but not only that, and only when they might be of interest to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Post things that no-one else could post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to write the same things that everyone else is writing. This means posts must have a personal angle, which sets up a tight balancing act with rule number one. Posts must be personal, but also of interest to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two rules don’t eliminate any of the post types I described above: I can, and will, still post travel pictures, introspections, and commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how long this burst lasts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve always struggled with blogging. I want to do it, I have things that I want to share. But it always happens in bursts, a few good posts create a high bar for future posts, which get half written but never published.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mt Ruapehu</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/07/27/mt-ruapehu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mt Ruapehu" /><published>2015-07-27T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2015-07-27T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/07/27/mt-ruapehu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/07/27/mt-ruapehu.html">&lt;p&gt;We caught the train up to Mt Ruapehu on the weekend and caught the chairlift up to the new Knoll Ridge Cafe which is a very cool building (and has won at least one architecture award).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-wide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Knoll Ridge Cafe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Knoll Ridge Cafe at Whakapapa Skifield, Mt Ruapehu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-interior.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inside the Knoll Ridge Cafe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Inside the Knoll Ridge Cafe, the Flat White was pretty decent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-close.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mountains reflected on the windows&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mountains reflected on the windows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-tables.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The view&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We caught the train up to Mt Ruapehu on the weekend and caught the chairlift up to the new Knoll Ridge Cafe which is a very cool building (and has won at least one architecture award).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lemon Curd</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/11/02/lemon-curd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lemon Curd" /><published>2014-11-02T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2014-11-02T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/11/02/lemon-curd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/11/02/lemon-curd.html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of last year my friend Joel introduced me to Lemon Curd, or more specifally, to Lemon Curd on toast. I’d had lemon curd before, it’s commonly used in desserts, but using it as a breakfast spread was new to me, and I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… I tried making Lemon Curd myself (sorry, this is turning into a cooking blog). I used the recipe provided by Joel which is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 large lemons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100g butter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 cups of sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;Instructions:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grate the rind &amp;amp; squeeze the juice of the lemons into a saucepan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut butter into small cubes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beat the eggs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the butter eggs and sugar to the saucepan and stir over a very low heat until the sugar has dissolved &amp;amp; the curd has thickened&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pour mixture into hot sterilized jar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let it stand to cool to room temperature then place in fridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lemon_curd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;There's lemon zest somewhere underneath all that sugar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s lemon zest somewhere underneath all that sugar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out pretty well! Ideally it would have been a bit thicker (I didn’t really have the patience for stirring slowly over a very low heat for too long), but the taste is just right.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">At the end of last year my friend Joel introduced me to Lemon Curd, or more specifally, to Lemon Curd on toast. I’d had lemon curd before, it’s commonly used in desserts, but using it as a breakfast spread was new to me, and I liked it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stuff by RSS</title><link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/26/stuff-by-rss.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stuff by RSS" /><published>2014-10-26T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2014-10-26T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/26/stuff-by-rss</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/26/stuff-by-rss.html">&lt;p&gt;I generally avoid mainstream news media sites, for content discovery at least, I often click links to their articles. I do find myself reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuff.co.nz&quot;&gt;Stuff&lt;/a&gt; though, and almost always regretting it. At one point I had stuff.co.nz routed to localhost in my hosts file so that my computer literally couldn’t access it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the reason I keep going back to Stuff is that there’s national news there that I don’t really get anywhere else. I started wondering, what would Stuff look like with a different editor, who wasn’t interested in maximising revenue, or catering to the lowest common denominator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday morning I read this tweet from Ben Gracewood:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How much will rates go up?&amp;#10;It is too early to say.&amp;quot;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nzherald&quot;&gt;@nzherald&lt;/a&gt; saved you a click. &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/rqqrFJyGxh&quot;&gt;http://t.co/rqqrFJyGxh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ben Gracewood (@nzben) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nzben/status/525334208437182464&quot;&gt;October 23, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Saved you a click”, is a common sight on Twitter. Editors have started writing headlines that deliberately omit a key fact so that readers are forced to click through and read the article (and view some ads in the process). By rewriting a headline, or including a few extra words, it’s possible to avoid the need to click through and read the whole article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the editor put the reader ahead of the advertiser and was &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to save you a click? The headlines and excerpts would be written to include as many facts as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the editor prioritised content based on their own opinions and ideas instead of catering to the lowest common denominator? The way content is arranged would change, entire sections of content would disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to build a Chrome Addon to layer some of this functionality on top of Stuff.co.nz, and in doing so came accross the Stuff RSS feeds. There’s an RSS feed for each page on the site and in my opinion, the feeds are better than the website itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example the headline &lt;strong&gt;‘Dodgy’ taxis shut down&lt;/strong&gt; on the Stuff homepage becomes &lt;strong&gt;$20 ‘sober driver’ taxi page shut down&lt;/strong&gt; in the RSS feed. &lt;strong&gt;Beware of backyard chickens&lt;/strong&gt; on the homepage becomes &lt;strong&gt;Backyard chicken lead poisoning alert&lt;/strong&gt; in the RSS feed, and so on. The RSS feeds also have useful excerpts (sadly not the full articles)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of a chrome addon, I came up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuffbyrss.dowse.co.nz/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stuff by RSS&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a minimalist alternative homepage for Stuff which may save you a click in some cases, and at the very least will spare you from ‘Stuff Nation’ and ‘Essential Mums’. &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuffbyrss.dowse.co.nz/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t replace the editorial team at Stuff, but maybe they don’t need to be completely replaced. To me it’s a clear improvement over the current Stuff homepage. I’d love to keep expanding the scope of Stuff by RSS from here to the point where headlines and excerpts are being rewritten and perhaps even additional content added.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I generally avoid mainstream news media sites, for content discovery at least, I often click links to their articles. I do find myself reading Stuff though, and almost always regretting it. At one point I had stuff.co.nz routed to localhost in my hosts file so that my computer literally couldn’t access it.</summary></entry></feed>