<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michael Dowse</title>
    <description>Software Developer, reader, and occasional [blogger](http://michaeldowse.name). Founder of Go Vocab. Born and raised in Wellington, New Zealand.
</description>
    <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 10:34:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 10:34:00 +1300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Budgeting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This year I’ve found myself with a regular routine and a regular income which seemed to be draining out of my bank account impossibly fast so I decided to have a go at budgeting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set a goal of spending $500 a week to spend, setting the rest aside for tax, savings, international travel, whatever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week $250 goes to a joint account to cover rent, bills and groceries. That leaves $250 to cover everything else: food, entertainment, transport and one off expenses like a new iPhone, clothes, haircuts, domestic travel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to note: I consider this money allocated for spending, not saving. So if I have money left at the end of the week then I should allocate it to larger purchases which are split across several weeks like a new iPhone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a neat app I use on my computer called Rescuetime which tracks how I use my computer and then categorizes my time as productive, neutral or unproductive. So an hour spent programming would be considered productive and an hour spent on Facebook would be considered unproductive. Of course I have control over which activities are classified as productive or unproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wondered if I could do he same think with my budgeting. The way I see it, money is something I can use to survive, but beyond that it can also be used to achieve my goals in life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I classified my expenses using these rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Expenses that are essential to survive (rent, groceries) are neutral.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Expenses that help me achieve my goals (a tent for tramping, a trip to Queenstown for the marathon) are productive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Expenses that do neither of the above (eating out, Netflix) are unproductive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are exceptions of course. For example, if I eat out with friends then I’ll count that expense as productive because spending time with friends is good and something I should do more of even though I haven’t explicitly stated it as a goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That probably sounds horribly confusing so far but it works, here’s what it looks like for the past 3 weeks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                    Week Ending 14/9	    Week Ending 21/9	    Week Ending 28/9
Total Spending      $410.06	              $434.42	              $409.08
Productive          $34.16	              $38.72	              $25.00
Neutral             $316.50	              $270.00	              $255.00
Unproductive        $59.40	              $125.70	              $129.08
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started budgeting this way the amount I’ve been spending per week has been steadily decreasing (which leaves more money for stuff like my upcoming trip to do the Queen Charlotte track). I think it’s one of those cases where just being aware of something is enough to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/09/29/budgeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/09/29/budgeting.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes from Startup Weekend Education</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentoring-is-hard&quot;&gt;Mentoring is hard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After coming second in two previous startup weekends and founding an education startup that wasn’t a complete failure I signed up to be a mentor this time around. To be honest, I found it quite challenging. With so many mentors and so much combined expertise I felt a but under qualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentors we also tried to use the Socratic method: teach by asking questions. While I could often spot flaws and invalidated assumptions in a teams work I struggled to rephrase criticisms as constructive questions that would steer the team on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;monetization-is-an-unsolved-problem-in-education&quot;&gt;Monetization is an unsolved problem in education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something we’ve struggled with a lot at Go Vocab. There is no proven model for monetizing an app used in the classroom. Maybe that’s not fair, there are proven models, but there’s no clear winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hoping to see some new ideas in this area at Startup Weekend but I was disappointed to see a lot of teams with vague monetization plans and a lot of social enterprises that seemed closer to charities than businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theres-still-a-lot-of-opportunity&quot;&gt;There’s still a lot of opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday night 45 people up to pitch their idea. Sure, some were near duplicates but that’s still a lot of ideas. Partly because of the monetization challenges mentioned above edtech, and specifically subject specific apps for use in the classroom has been largely ignored&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no grand conclusion to make. If you’re at all interested in startup weekend and haven’t been to one then you definitely should. It’s an amazing experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +1200</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/09/22/startup-weekend.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/09/22/startup-weekend.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Housing availability: Renting vs buying</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about buying a house. I’m currently living in Newtown for the second time and I like it here, it’s close to town, but not in town and has it’s own community feel. A couple of months ago I started going to open homes to get a feel for the market. As time goes by I’m more and more ready to buy a house, and I’m becoming increasingly disappointed with what’s available on the market. Everything is expensive, really expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After contemplating the reality that I may still be renting next year I had a brief look at the places to rent in Newtown on TradeMe. There are currently 57 properties available to rent in Newtown, which seemed like a lot considering that there are only 16 properties for sale. I was curious to see if this ratio was part of a bigger trend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                Rent      Buy
NZ              10,172    Over 32,000
Auckland City   1,507     1,674
Wellington      913       952
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so the disparity I observed in Newtown isn’t a nationwide trend. In general there are far more properties for sale than for rent, but in cities the split is pretty much 50/50. That makes sense. Let’s take a closer look at some popular Wellington suburbs[1]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                Rent      Buy       Rent/Buy
Brooklyn        36        25        1.44
Churton Park    10        28        0.3571
Haitaitai       23        21        1.0952
Johnsonville    34        49        0.6938
Karori          49        46        1.0652
Kelburn         34        19        1.7895
Khandallah      32        49        0.6531
Kilbirnie       21        6         3.5
Miramar         23        32        0.7188
Mt Cook         26        30        0.8667
Mt Victoria     41        13        3.1538
Newlands        18        48        0.375
Newtown         57        16        3.5625
Oriental Bay    16        39        0.4103
Tawa            14        47        0.2979
Te Aro          59        109       0.5413
Thorndon        37        45        0.8222
Wadestown       23        8         2.875
CBD             158       112       1.4107
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out, the ratio of houses for sale vs to rent varies widely. Newtown has the highest ratio of houses to rent vs houses for sale (Kilbirnie is a close second but at much lower volume). In contrast, Tawa and Newlands have far more houses for sale than for rent. Off the top of my head I can think of a few possible explanations for these variations, but I don’t want to jump to conclusions. One complicating factor is that many rental properties in Wellington are on 12 month leases which renew early in the year (usually February).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Suburbs with either more than 20 properties for sale or more than 20 properties available to rent based on TradeMe listings on the 14th September, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +1200</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/09/15/housing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/09/15/housing.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
