<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michael Dowse</title>
    <description>Software Developer, reader, and occasional blogger. Founder of Go Vocab. Born and raised in Wellington, New Zealand.
</description>
    <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://michael.dowse.co.nz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2016 17:28:23 +1200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2016 17:28:23 +1200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tasty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you use Facebook, you’ve probably noticed the recipe videos from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/buzzfeedtasty/?fref=ts&quot;&gt;Tasty&lt;/a&gt; frequently featuring on your news feed. They’re everywhere right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go viral on Facebook a video needs to catch your attention, without any sound, while you’re scrolling through the news feed. The Tasty videos do that, I stop scrolling every time. Here’s one for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fbuzzfeedtasty%2Fvideos%2F1741611326091509%2F&amp;amp;show_text=1&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;425&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, I wasn’t particularly surprised to find out that Tasty is a part of Buzzfeed. I normally don’t like viral things in my feed but I do like these Tasty videos and I’ve been able to rationalise a couple of possible justifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooking is a good thing that we should do more of and Tasty videos encourage that&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people agree that we should cook more. Just like we should exercise more, or read more books. These are things that most people feel are positive influences on their lives, and that we should do more of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could say that reality shows like MasterChef encourage cooking, and for some people they probably do, but they also promote sitting on the couch watching other people cook, and then paying exorbitant prices to eat a meal prepared in a kitched overseen by a “MasterChef”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasty videos serve less as entertainment and more as inspiration. While you couldn’t make the meal just from watching the video, you &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; could, and there’s always a link to the full recipe attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They promote &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; cooking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasty recipes tend to start from scratch, using basic ingredients. There are no cake mixes, or pre-made anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only inputs into the videos are relatively unprocessed ingredients that can be found in any supermarket, showing a committment to recipes that people can actually make at home. It’s just good business sense really, as the recipes need to appeal to people all over the world. Some of the competitors who have popped up are less principled, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/foodbyshared/videos/1018342061536144/?fref=nf&quot;&gt;like this example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipes are often not particularly simple (though the video format makes them look deceptively so). They encourage the idea that cooking takes effort, but that your effort will be rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convinced? Here’s a couple more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fbuzzfeedtasty%2Fvideos%2F1741600096092632%2F&amp;amp;show_text=1&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;425&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fbuzzfeedtasty%2Fvideos%2F1741588772760431%2F&amp;amp;show_text=1&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;425&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1200</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/04/17/tasty.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/04/17/tasty.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Choosing a Socially Responsible Kiwisaver Scheme</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently found myself making significant contributions to Kiwisaver for the first time so I decided to put an appropriate amount of effort into choosing the best Kiwisaver scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all my spending, I try to follow Ghandi’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/30/opinion/falser-words-were-never-spoken.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;misquoted&lt;/a&gt; advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  Be the change that you wish to see in the world
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to investing, this means investing in companies which are making a positive contribution to society &amp;amp; the environment. From my cursory analysis of the 189 available Kiwisaver schemes there are 5 that are specifically targeted at investors like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quaystreet-balanced-sri-fundhttpfundfindersortedorgnzfundcraigs-investment-partners-kiwistart-defined-scheme---balanced-sri-fund-craigs-investment-partners-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/craigs-investment-partners-kiwistart-defined-scheme---balanced-sri-fund-craigs-investment-partners-/&quot;&gt;QuayStreet Balanced SRI Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Craigs Investment Partners&lt;/em&gt; this fund invests in investments that Craigs “deems to be environmentally sustainable or socially responsible”. A pretty broad mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Balanced&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 318&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $4,713,552&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socially-responsible-investment-growth-fundhttpfundfindersortedorgnzfundgrosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/grosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited/&quot;&gt;Socially Responsible Investment Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Grosvenor Investment Management&lt;/em&gt;, this fund “will exclude companies and other investments where the underlying activities are principally involved in the tobacco, alcohol, gambling and armaments industries” which is a pretty low bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Growth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 1,556&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $16,999,866&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socially-responsible-investment-balanced-fundhttpfundfindersortedorgnzfundgrosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-balanced-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/grosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-balanced-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited/&quot;&gt;Socially Responsible Investment Balanced Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Grosvenor Investment Management&lt;/em&gt;, this fund will exclude “investments which do not satisfy certain socially responsible investment criteria”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Balanced&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 4,031&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $17,854,622&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sustainable-international-share-fundhttpfundfindersortedorgnzfundoneanswer-kiwisaver-scheme---sustainable-international-share-fund-anz-new-zealand-investments-limited&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/oneanswer-kiwisaver-scheme---sustainable-international-share-fund-anz-new-zealand-investments-limited/&quot;&gt;Sustainable International Share Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;ANZ&lt;/em&gt;, this fund invests exclusively in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://funds.ft.com/uk/Tearsheet/Summary?s=LU0119216553:EUR&quot;&gt;Global Sustainable Equity Fund&lt;/a&gt; which “combines respect for social principles (such as human rights, non-discrimination and the issue of child labour) and environmental principles with good financial prospects”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite only investing on one fund, this scheme still manages to charge above average fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Aggressive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 362&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $4,305,412&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ethica-fundhttpfundfindersortedorgnzfundsuperlife---ethica-pool-superlife-limited&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/superlife---ethica-pool-superlife-limited/&quot;&gt;Ethica Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided by &lt;em&gt;Superlife&lt;/em&gt;, this fund “looks to avoid investments in the areas of pornography, gambling, tobacco, alcohol, armaments and fossil fuel extraction”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Profile:&lt;/strong&gt; Balanced&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Members:&lt;/strong&gt; 937&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Value:&lt;/strong&gt; $12,406,942&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other options. Craigs offers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigsip.com/services/kiwisaver.aspx&quot;&gt;a scheme where you can pick your own stocks&lt;/a&gt;, and there may be other schemes which invest in a responsible manner but don’t explicitly flag that as their intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking purely at social responsibility it seems like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fundfinder.sorted.org.nz/fund/grosvenor-kiwisaver-scheme---socially-responsible-investment-fund-grosvenor-investment-management-limited/&quot;&gt;Socially Responsible Investment Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt; is the best option, but I will be following up some of the others for more details of their investment criteria. There are other factors to consider of course, such as risk profile, returns, and fees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/03/10/kiwisaver.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2016/03/10/kiwisaver.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Plymouth</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;New Plymouth is a lot cooler than it used to be. Som and I headed up there for the weekend a few months ago. In no particular order, some highlights were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-coastal-walkway&quot;&gt;The coastal walkway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/walkway.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coastal walkway is lovely, the water was a bit wild the day we went which made it all the more interesting. Unfortunately not caught on camera: when Som turned to photograph this sign a wave came up from behind and she got soaked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-govett-brewster-len-lye-gallery&quot;&gt;The Govett-Brewster Len Lye gallery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/lenlye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exterior is probably actually the highlight, but the stuff inside is cool too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mount-taranaki&quot;&gt;Mount Taranaki&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/taranaki.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was too much snow to climb Mount Taranaki without actual mountaineering skills but I’ve climbed it on a previous trip and it’s a pretty awesome hike. When we went in the height of summer there was still snow at the top. If nothing else, it’s worth a trip to the visitors center halfway up the mountain for some sweet views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;street-art&quot;&gt;Street Art&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/newplymouth/bmd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BMD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Plymouth is the home of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmdisyourfriend.com/&quot;&gt;BMD&lt;/a&gt; and there is a lot of their work, and cool work by other artists, throughout the city center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;food--drink-that-was-up-to-the-standard-of-us-city-folk&quot;&gt;Food &amp;amp; drink that was up to the standard of us city folk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For coffee, head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ozonecoffee.com/bean-store.php&quot;&gt;Ozone Coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For brunch, head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thefederalstore.com/&quot;&gt;The Federal Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For dinner, head to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/PEKAREN-696952050381686/&quot;&gt;Pekaren&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus:&lt;/strong&gt; Our AirBnB host was a nudist with a house full of &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; artwork, though the wall to wall mirrors in the shower were a little intimidating.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/new-plymouth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/new-plymouth.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rules of the blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve always struggled with blogging. I want to do it, I have things that I want to share. But it always happens in bursts, a few good posts create a high bar for future posts, which get half written but never published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly I agonise over what I should be blogging about. Should I post my travel pictures? Should I be posting my own introspections? Or should I be posting my commentary on things? To help reduce my future agonising I’ve come up with two rules for this blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Posts things of interest to others&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a public blog, not a personal diary. It’s not for my aimless musings. I mean it is for that, but not only that, and only when they might be of interest to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Post things that no-one else could post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to write the same things that everyone else is writing. This means posts must have a personal angle, which sets up a tight balancing act with rule number one. Posts must be personal, but also of interest to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two rules don’t eliminate any of the post types I described above: I can, and will, still post travel pictures, introspections, and commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how long this burst lasts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/blogging-goals.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/12/19/blogging-goals.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mt Ruapehu</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We caught the train up to Mt Ruapehu on the weekend and caught the chairlift up to the new Knoll Ridge Cafe which is a very cool building (and has won at least one architecture award).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-wide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Knoll Ridge Cafe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Knoll Ridge Cafe at Whakapapa Skifield, Mt Ruapehu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-interior.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inside the Knoll Ridge Cafe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Inside the Knoll Ridge Cafe, the Flat White was pretty decent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-close.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mountains reflected on the windows&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mountains reflected on the windows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ruapehu/cafe-tables.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The view&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +1200</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/07/27/mt-ruapehu.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2015/07/27/mt-ruapehu.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lemon Curd</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of last year my friend Joel introduced me to Lemon Curd, or more specifally, to Lemon Curd on toast. I’d had lemon curd before, it’s commonly used in desserts, but using it as a breakfast spread was new to me, and I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… I tried making Lemon Curd myself (sorry, this is turning into a cooking blog). I used the recipe provided by Joel which is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 large lemons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100g butter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 cups of sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;Instructions:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grate the rind &amp;amp; squeeze the juice of the lemons into a saucepan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut butter into small cubes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beat the eggs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the butter eggs and sugar to the saucepan and stir over a very low heat until the sugar has dissolved &amp;amp; the curd has thickened&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pour mixture into hot sterilized jar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let it stand to cool to room temperature then place in fridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lemon_curd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;There&#39;s lemon zest somewhere underneath all that sugar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s lemon zest somewhere underneath all that sugar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out pretty well! Ideally it would have been a bit thicker (I didn’t really have the patience for stirring slowly over a very low heat for too long), but the taste is just right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/11/02/lemon-curd.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/11/02/lemon-curd.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stuff by RSS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I generally avoid mainstream news media sites, for content discovery at least, I often click links to their articles. I do find myself reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuff.co.nz&quot;&gt;Stuff&lt;/a&gt; though, and almost always regretting it. At one point I had stuff.co.nz routed to localhost in my hosts file so that my computer literally couldn’t access it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the reason I keep going back to Stuff is that there’s national news there that I don’t really get anywhere else. I started wondering, what would Stuff look like with a different editor, who wasn’t interested in maximising revenue, or catering to the lowest common denominator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday morning I read this tweet from Ben Gracewood:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How much will rates go up?&amp;#10;It is too early to say.&amp;quot;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nzherald&quot;&gt;@nzherald&lt;/a&gt; saved you a click. &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/rqqrFJyGxh&quot;&gt;http://t.co/rqqrFJyGxh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ben Gracewood (@nzben) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nzben/status/525334208437182464&quot;&gt;October 23, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Saved you a click”, is a common sight on Twitter. Editors have started writing headlines that deliberately omit a key fact so that readers are forced to click through and read the article (and view some ads in the process). By rewriting a headline, or including a few extra words, it’s possible to avoid the need to click through and read the whole article. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the editor put the reader ahead of the advertiser and was &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to save you a click? The headlines and excerpts would be written to include as many facts as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the editor prioritised content based on their own opinions and ideas instead of catering to the lowest common denominator? The way content is arranged would change, entire sections of content would disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to build a Chrome Addon to layer some of this functionality on top of Stuff.co.nz, and in doing so came accross the Stuff RSS feeds. There’s an RSS feed for each page on the site and in my opinion, the feeds are better than the website itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example the headline &lt;strong&gt;‘Dodgy’ taxis shut down&lt;/strong&gt; on the Stuff homepage becomes &lt;strong&gt;$20 ‘sober driver’ taxi page shut down&lt;/strong&gt; in the RSS feed. &lt;strong&gt;Beware of backyard chickens&lt;/strong&gt; on the homepage becomes &lt;strong&gt;Backyard chicken lead poisoning alert&lt;/strong&gt; in the RSS feed, and so on. The RSS feeds also have useful excerpts (sadly not the full articles)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of a chrome addon, I came up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuffbyrss.dowse.co.nz/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stuff by RSS&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a minimalist alternative homepage for Stuff which may save you a click in some cases, and at the very least will spare you from ‘Stuff Nation’ and ‘Essential Mums’. &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuffbyrss.dowse.co.nz/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t replace the editorial team at Stuff, but maybe they don’t need to be completely replaced. To me it’s a clear improvement over the current Stuff homepage. I’d love to keep expanding the scope of Stuff by RSS from here to the point where headlines and excerpts are being rewritten and perhaps even additional content added.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/26/stuff-by-rss.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/26/stuff-by-rss.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cold Flat White</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year the Iced Mocha was my drink; a cold coffee with chocolate, and either ice cream or ice. Some would say it’s not a real coffee, I say it’s delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem impractical to drink iced coffee in winter, it didn’t stop me, but some find the idea a bit jarring. Anyway, now that summer is approaching there’s no excuse not to embrace iced coffee. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I discovered my favorite coffee of all: the Cold Flat White from &lt;a href=&quot;http://peoplescoffee.co.nz/&quot;&gt;People’s Coffee&lt;/a&gt; (conveniently located only a few blocks from my house in Newtown). The Cold Flat White is a simple drink: cold brewed coffee, milk, and a touch of Maple Syrup. It’s delicious and I strongly recommend trying it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two problems: it costs $6 and is only available in Newtown. I needed an affordable and never ending supply of this stuff so I started making my own. That’s right, I make Cold Flat Whites at home and you can too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-cold-brew-coffee&quot;&gt;Step 1: Cold Brew Coffee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out &lt;a href=&quot;http://boingboing.net/2013/07/20/cheap-easy-no-mess-cold-brew.html&quot;&gt;cold brewing coffee is stupidly simple&lt;/a&gt;. Get some medium grind coffee, put it in a giant teabag (more specifically a nut milk bag, like you’d use to make almond milk), put it in some water and leave it overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was doubtful that the giant teabag approach could work as well as a Chemex filter, and having never used a Chemex I’m still not sure. It worked pretty well though, the resulting coffee was smooth and not at all gritty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Doesn&#39;t look appetizing, but...&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Doesn’t look appetizing, but…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a night of brewing squeeze the giant teabag so as to extract every last bit of coffee goodness. Then you’re left with a strong cold brewed coffee essence, I wouldn’t recommend drinking this straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you used a whole bag of coffee like I did then you’ll have a lot of this coffee essence. That’s alright, it will last a while, store it in the fridge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-make-a-cold-flat-white&quot;&gt;Step 2: Make a Cold Flat White&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you’re ready to assemble a cold flat white. I’m still experimenting with the ratios here but it goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A couple of drops of Maple Syrup in the bottom of a glass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fill the glass with 50% coffee essence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fill the rest of the glass with milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s really all there is to it, enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to keep perfecting this: the next step is to increase the quality of the ingredients: really good freshly ground coffee, really good fresh organic milk, perhaps from Lewis Road Creamery, and real Maple Syrup (I must confess I’m currently using Maple Flavoured syrup). &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/19/cold-flat-white.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/19/cold-flat-white.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Orongorongo River Tramp</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend Som and I went for a quick overnight tramp into the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-visit/wellington-kapiti/wellington/catchpool-and-orongorongo-valleys/&quot;&gt;Orongorongo Valley&lt;/a&gt;. The goal was to test out a bunch of new gear and generally make sure we’re ready to tackle some bigger tramps like the Queen Charlotte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/orongorongos-track.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The track in to the river&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The track in to the river&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We followed the track along the Catchpool Valley until it met the Orongorongo Valley, then walked upriver a bit until we found a suitable campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/orongorongos-river.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;In the river valley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the river valley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Dinner we cooked pasta with  eggplant and mushrooms and for breakfast we had Banana Loaf (prepared earlier). Then on sunday morning we walked back the way we came in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was only one slight mishap: I left the car keys at the campsite and didn’t notice until we were 15 minutes into the walk home. Thankfully they were exactly where I left them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/orongorongos-camp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our campsite for the night&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our campsite for the night&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All our gear worked great and so now we’re all set for the next adventure. The weather was perfect and it didn’t rain at all, which is great, though it means that the waterproofness of my new tent remains untested.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/12/orongorongo-river-tramp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/12/orongorongo-river-tramp.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The West Wing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently achieved a longstanding relationship goal: get my girlfriend Som to love The West Wing as much as I do, or at least almost as much as I do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, you have to understand; I love Aaron Sorkin’s Tv shows. Sports Night, The West Wing, Studio 60 and The Newsroom, I love them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Wing is the best of them all for a few reasons I can put my finger on and many I can’t. Sorkin’s dramatic style feels right at home in the White House. It has the strongest female characters. And of course it’s the only one of Sorkin’s shows to last more than 2 seasons (The Newsroom is about to start its third and final season, but those are short HBO seasons). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we first met Som didn’t have the same level of interest in tv shows written by Aaron Sorkin, which is to say she had no interest at all. I forced her to watch a few episodes of Studio 60 and while she was very tolerant, I could tell that her heart wasn’t in it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave up for a while, occasionally forcing upon her a particularly good West Wing episode until one day we started watching Parks and Recreation together. Parks is a great show; it’s funny, has an awesome cast including the perfect female lead in Amy Poehler and tackles serious moral issues. It also has a lot in common with The West Wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parks is a show about idealistic left leaning government employees who pour their heart and soul into their work but due to the nature of politics achieve only middling results. As is the West Wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we started Parks and Recreation. Som loved it. We got through all 6 seasons in about a month. Then, in that moment of despair after watching the last episode of a show when you realize that there’s no more, I suggested we try The West Wing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was keen, she was ready. We just finished watching the first season of The West Wing and she loved it. She laughed, she cried, she’s hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up: Sports Night! Well, after finishing the next 6 seasons of The West Wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS - If you haven’t watched The West Wing you really, really should. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/05/the-west-wing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://michael.dowse.co.nz/2014/10/05/the-west-wing.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
